recently it is it has become so popular
in 1989
and even java
and one more thing is what see i think
those relevant ads they show me
in many areas this is one application of
right
you know save your time also
language
down these features so it is also python
because it is open source anyone can
in terms of developers in terms of the
python so there are many career
not support this version now so will you
so this is the first lecture of our
python code so you can say python course
we will see in this video introduction
to python right
like you can say some features of this
language application areas who are using
this python why this is so popular
nowadays some features this kind of
thing we'll be discussing in this video
about python or python
i'll pronounce it as python right okay
now see python is nowadays the most
popular programming language but you can
say it is the fastest growing
programming language nowadays it's not
like that it is new language because you
you know you think that
so it is a
new language no
the concept of python came into picture
was you know the concept of java or came
into picture in 1995 so it is before
java
right but
recently in past few years like
python has become so much popular and
why so that also will discuss
right now basically in every area python
is being used right now the main areas
are machine learning data science
artificial intelligence see nowadays the
data is a big problem many companies
like you can say your facebook
youtube any shopping websites
they are having
data of billions of users right and how
they manage that data
you have noticed
if you suppose uh
nowadays i
you know a search for especially chicken
carry kurtas
right
so
i have i've been looking for these
kurtas on two or three website shopping
websites and whenever i open any other
website you know for study
that kind of thing
so
now ads of those chicken curry kurtas
and all so have they come to know the
advertisers like how they come to know
that i'm interested in buying those
chicken curry kurtas
so this is what they have analyzed my
data
how
many websites i have visited in which
how you know i'm interested so they have
analyzed that data they have collected
my data they have analyzed that data and
according to that they have mind you can
say some
pattern they have formed
and they come to they come to know that
i am interested in chicken keri kurta so
they show me the relevant ad
i think you must have noticed this thing
also
right
so this task is what this analysis of
data and all
in this also python is being used
right
so
this language and see in many areas like
whether it's software development it's
web development software testing machine
learning artificial intelligence data
science game development making of any
apps mobile apps desktop app websites or
web apps anything hacking even hacking
in many areas
right now python is being used and it's
not like that small companies are using
this language no the big giants
companies are using this language maybe
the main language or supportive type of
language as a support language
you can select like google uh youtube
cura instagram these companies are using
these big giants are using this language
and the person who are using it
researchers scientists
software developers software engineers
software testers game developers
mainly
data analyst
and even school going kids
they are also
learning or you can see using this
language
see
because
you know researchers and scientists they
want us
like they don't want to you know uh
utilize or you can say wasted their time
by learning a complicated language and
python is easy language so they talk
they
went for this language python language
so that is why recently this this field
is a you know on boom machine learning
artificial intelligence data science
this kind of thing so that is why with
that field python came into picture
because they these kind of people
researchers scientists so they are
working in this field they want a simple
language to work on right they don't
want to waste their time on learning a
complicated type of language python is
very simple very easy to understand
language so they took it for this
language and that is why this uh
language has become so much popular
within the you know recent years so
white has become so popular because
first thing is it is easy to learn easy
to understand and it has wide range of
applications i have told you in how many
areas almost in every area
it's been used
second thing
you can write down you can solve any
problem with
fewer lines of code suppose you want to
print hello world in c language
so that those header files main function
and printf hello one in c plus plus also
header files std name space std main
function and all in java
those you can say the main function
system uh sorry public static void mean
then system dot outdoor printer and then
hello world this kind of thing in
python simply what you need to write
print
hello world
that's it
nothing else a simple line
nothing else
so
in fewer lines of code you can solve
complex problems
right and more easily you can understand
this course so it will
another benefit and it is high level
language you don't need to be aware
about those memory management type of
thing like in c you have to aware you
have to you know keep track of you have
to manage the memory manually but here
automatic memory management is there it
is high level language so you can do
more
with
less
right with the writing you can say less
code you can do more in this it is
object-oriented programming language but
it's not like that it doesn't support
that paradigm procedural and functional
it supports multiple paradigms
object-oriented procedural as well as
functional
right it is multi-paradigm language it
is general purpose language almost in
every field
for making everything you can use this
it's multi-purpose language
it is
interpreted language these are some
features of python you can just note
is interpreted language without compiled
language
right
and one more feature of this it is open
source right so that is why it is having
a huge community and rich library many
ill
you know inbuilt packages modules
functions those
you can use in your program without
writing those functions from scratch
contribute
in this right they can write down their
packages or functions or modules and
they can contribute it is open source
anyone can use
those inbuilt functions libraries and
all
right like in cnc plus
also we have some libraries in there
predefined functions are there these are
already defined function like uh if
for string concatenation we use directly
a function str tap so the definition of
that function is already in those
libraries you don't have to write down
the definition of that function you
don't have to tell the compiler you just
use that header file string dot h and
you can call that function because it is
already been defined in the library by
some
other people so by someone else
so same
it is also having rich library because
it is open source so
and huge community it is having if you
are finding any difficulty in this
so there are many forums discussion
forums you can post your queries and
definitely you will get answer for
example some libraries are you can say
numpy pandas tensorflow for machine
learning and data science while in this
field they use that library see
basically libraries are what
some codes are written codes so for some
basic functions are written on those
libraries so that programmers don't have
to write down those function from
scratch and they can reuse those
functions in their own program right so
that
obviously it will save time of any
programmer right because they are using
they are reusing that function
like for making chapatis you need atta
right so just go to any shop maybe you
can buy whole wheat or
atta right but the process behind that
thing generally farmers do that process
that long process
right they have done for you
so they have built those things for you
you just have to go and buy you can
reuse that you don't have to do the
whole process from scratch because it
will take definitely long time
and you don't know definitely most of
you don't know how to
do that farming process
so same thing those inbuilt libraries
packages modules functions are there
programmers can reuse those functions
and so it saves the time of programmers
and many frameworks are also there like
django flash
if you are interested in web development
right
and i told you like automatic memory
management is there in this language
right and it is extensible language
right you can extend you can support
more features can be supported you know
can be added like more libraries or
functions can be added because it is
open source anyone can contribute
in this thing in this open source school
right
and there are lots of career
opportunities also i'm sure this point
is very important for you guys yeah
there is lots of career opportunities
for this in this field
for this language because you know i
told you this is one of the fastest
growing language
companies using this language you know
the big giants like youtube cura
instagram google these companies are all
sort of thing just using this language
opportunities and average salary is also
high like it's from 8 to 12 per nm
so that is why it is so popular and i'm
sure you are aware about now this
language some features who are using it
the application areas of python and all
so please make down your own notes if
you have any doubt you can let me know
in comment section you can ask me right
and we'll be using python 3.x the latest
version of 3.x because python two point
x that version is obsolete now it's no
longer supported
uh from january 2020.
so they have declared that uh they'll
work on python three point x version the
latest version whatever is there
so in the next video
we will see
history of this language first
because
you know before going to battle better
know your enemy
so we'll see history of this language
properly like the inventor of this
language how when
why he developed this language why this
is called as the name python so these
thing will be discussing in next video
right so i'll see you in the next video
till then bye